A Guide to the Population Council records, Demographic Division and Technical Assistance Division files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 12 FA1432
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Demographic Division and Technical Assistance Division files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 12
1969-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
FA1432
2.26 Cubic Feet 4 legal-size document boxes and 1 letter-size document box.
Arrangement
Original order, as received.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Personnel files are restricted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
This series contains a small selection of program files, project proposals and correspondence from the Demographic Division and the Technical Assistance Division. The majority of the series documents summer programs in the early 1970s.
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
- Demographic Division, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Organization of Demographic Division, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Demographic Division - Key Issues, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Demographic Division - Space, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Demographic Division - Office Move, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Training of Demographers, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Population Growth Studies, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Summer Project in Demographic Research 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Technical Assistance Division (TAD) - Research and Evaluation Unit, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8a)
- Technical Assistance Division (TAD) - Research and Evaluation Unit - Seminars, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8b)
- Technical Assistance Division (TAD) - Research and Evaluation Unit - Seminars, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8c)
- Technical Assistance Division (TAD) - Research and Evaluation Unit, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8d)
- Technical Assistance Division (TAD) - Research and Evaluation Unit - Evaluation System for Social Service Delivery Program, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8e)
- Summer Project in Demographic Research 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Summer Program - Staff Projects 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Summer Interns 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted - Personnel files
- Summer Intern Program 1970 - General (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Summer Interns 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Summer Intern Program 1971 - General, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Summer Interns 1971 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
- Summer Project in Demographic Research 1972 - General (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Summer Interns 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Summer Intern Program 1973 - General (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Summer Seminars, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Summer Program 1973 - Project Proposals (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Summer Interns 1973 - Staff Coordination (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Summer Interns 1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Summer Interns 1973 - Declined (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Summer Interns 1973 - Declined (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Summer Interns 1974 - Declined (Box 5, Folder 27-28)